all right
Uh some of you know today is a special
day for
me Uh July 28th is special day for
me 49 years ago
uh when I was 22
uh I saw emptiness directly
I'm
from and
uh and I had a a bodhic experience of
bodhicida and
uh I didn't tell anybody for many years
uh but uh when you see emptiness
directly
uh you are struggling to think of
something in the world which is
similar and the closest thing in the
normal world is a
diamond for many
reasons
Uh so that's why I I joined the diamond
business and I worked uh because I
wanted to touch diamonds every
day and uh I went
to 30 jewelry
stores in my small town area
in New
Jersey uh where I was staying in a
monastery and nobody would hire
me It's like trying to join the mafia
because you can steal a million dollars
in two minutes you know
Then I got very good luck and uh I found
a new company was starting in New
York and I worked there for 19
years just because I want to touch a
diamond every
day Then by accident it became
successful
Okay But it wasn't the purpose to make
money I just want to touch the diamonds
every
day So
uh so today is a special day for
me And uh as I get more grandpa and more
grandpa
I decide to tell people
if they don't believe it's
okay Uh but if you do believe it's very
good for
you So
uh I had an idea for this class
So every year I have to write a new uh
DCI
level and every year we teach 140,000
people
DCI and uh every year I have to write
three 400page
manual Uh so this year I wanted to focus
on the good night club good night book
club It's funny thing happened in uh
Arizona I call it goodn night book
club Then everybody says Gishla started
goodn night book club
Then Juan
Hustle he he has his new
show He's in a
rush He don't say good night book club
He say good
nightclub Then when he's really busy he
says nightclub
Then everyone thinks I'm
dancing Anyway uh the new DCI level for
this
year Uh it will focus a lot about
uh this idea to put away your cell phone
put away your computer for eight hours
And it's very very powerful to to kick
out your cell phone for the whole night
It's very it makes you very clearminded
Okay It's better than meditation
So
uh in this new DCI level uh we have to
suggest some books paper books that
people can read when they go to
bed Then there's a lot of there are some
countries in the world uh where you're
not allowed to publish
books Uh so my books are very popular in
those countries
There's one legal book in China
uh the diamond cutter business book
and it sold like millions of
copies in Russia It's a number two
bestselling foreign
book but I don't have any way to tell
those people about all my books
But we are allowed to publish the DCI
manual So I thought to put a little
piece of every book in the
manual There's 120 books
And I So I'm putting I'm I'm preparing
like a chocolate sampler
of all those books maybe 20 pages 30
pages from each book
Then it's good because I have to clean
up all of my
books So this week I was cleaning up a
book called The Garden
first picture Yeah
Uh this was kind of the first book I
wrote And there's a it's a story It's
not uh it's it's
fiction but it's true mostly
So I had a
This morning I thought I would like to
read you a
chapter about uh seeing emptiness
directly
Okay Uh so uh I had an idea
um just to have
fun and uh I won't read uh I'll just
read easy way like comfortable
way and she doesn't even know I'm going
to do it
So a lot of pressure for her
But I'll go
slow and I'll I'll speak in normal
English not bo
and it's like a vacation for you guys
Uh you just
relax Your ab is telling you a story
but don't forget it in your life
Uh then I don't know if we're going to
have time
If we can't finish I'll finish this
afternoon Okay
And uh if we finish early we can start
the photographs earlier Okay
Okay Uh deal
Okay Okay Here we go And uh to punish
you
I'm going to teach you directly from the
angel devil text which is very confusing
So morning is a good time for spiritual
things and uh evening is a good time for
confusing things
Okay so here we go
And I'm just going to paraphrase it Okay
Uh so I was a quiet bookworm I just like
to read
books But in the garden uh I had studied
with Shanti
Deva So a little bit I became a a
warrior Warrior in this book means satva
The Sanskrit is sata and bodhic sattva
means enlightened
warrior So I was a warrior but the
battlefield was my normal home
This guy is renting a small room in a
small
monastery and he's working in a
library Uh and so he's starting to see
his whole little world in a special way
Uh before I met all of these masters in
the garden
I felt like my life was uh living in a
shopping mall
and I'm just going from store to store
to get things you know
But after they taught me about bodhis
sava
uh even though I was still a small
person in the
world I felt like I was a knight in
shining armor
and When I met people
when I meet people
I feel like they are all my
children and uh every time I meet
somebody I try to be nice to
them and I will say some nice thing to
them but um and if they
are ready I will tell them something
about emptiness or something like
that And so I was more and more happy
every
day Uh but I also knew that I wasn't
finished with my education
Uh and I felt like a horse who comes
closer and closer to the water
And I wanted to find uh perfection
and I wanted to help my mother who
died and I wanted to meet um Vajioini
again
In this book she's called the golden one
I think
by the way uh after I wrote the book
I taught it in
Mongolia and there was a famous Tonka
painter in the audience
He painted that Tonka on the left side
And if you know uh diamond wave practice
uh the the fire coming out of the monk's
heart It has four
parts Uh and it's a
[Music]
So very famous diamond
way and uh so the whole painting has
special meaning Okay
So I was hoping to go back to the garden
and meet her again
Uh and there is a
garden
Okay So
the maybe it take too long
the the date was uh 28th of July the
book says
and it was summertime in the
garden And I came I came there late at
night and uh this garden is in Arizona
in the desert It's very
hot And there's a beautiful tree
there It's a carob carob tree
It has a long seam Ah And you can make
chocolate from the seeds Cacao Yeah Not
not not cacao
It makes a huge uh beautiful tree lives
for many
years The seed always grows the same
size in the whole world
If you plant carob tree in Arizona or
you plant it in Mexico City or you plant
it in Spain it doesn't matter The seed
will be exactly the same
size and from that carob word comes
carrot The word carrot like one karat
diamond two carat diamond three carat
diamond Uh because in the ancient times
they will use carob seed to weigh the
diamonds
So by accident it's a diamond tree
the picture you can
see on the left up on the left
[Music]
Okay Uh I sat down and started to
meditate in the
garden and uh in the garden I learned to
meditate from some of the Buddhist
[Music]
saints So in that story uh each chapter
a different uh Buddhist saint comes to
teach the young men
Is that book in in in Mexico i don't
know
All right Uh I know it's in Spain I
don't know if it's in Mexico Okay
Okay Then uh I sensed
uh somebody was coming into the garden
Uh there's a gate to the garden Uh and
there's a rose garden there Red red red
roses And uh then I saw it's
not it's uh I call her the golden one in
the book Yeah Okay
Then I saw it's a
monk and uh you know a very beautiful
monk and uh then I realize uh the last
uh master to visit me in the garden is
the Buddha himself
Uh he was not tall but
medium Uh little bit uh not little bit
thin and very shy
Uh and he always moves very gracefully
uh and impossible to guess his
age but maybe 27 28 years
old Uh and his whole expression is very
simple Uh I mistyped something I have to
fix Okay uh
not a lot and very uh modest no
pride Uh but super intelligent
face Uh and his skin is different from
human
skin and it has a kind of a
light soft light not like not like those
light
And he has bare feet He's not wearing
any shoes
And then I thought uh uncontrollably I
have
to then he's like sit down sit down
And I sit down on the grass in front of
the there's a stone bench or wooden
bench Okay
and he sat on the
bench and he looks uh shy like a young
girl like a young lady He's kind of he
looks kind of shy
Yeah Uh after a while he reached his
hand out out to me
Then I saw he has a red rose in his
hand and he didn't say
anything and he's just like look at it
you
know and he didn't say
anything so I just look at the rose in
his
hand then I was too shy to look at his
face
I just look at the
rose Uh then he suddenly he took the
rose
back and he touched my chin
like look in my
eyes and then he said one word
Oh
uh and then he closed my eyes with his
hand but he keeps the fingers
there Then uh when he touched my eyes I
I meditate on a rose the rose
picture Then he opened my eyes
again and he's still holding the
rose and he said "Do not think
rose." Then when somebody tells you not
to think about something
so I try not to think about roast
And I tried not to have the picture of
his hand with the rose you
know And uh then he opened his hand
again He said "Open your
eyes." And then just for a second I
don't see a rose
I see
little corners of the
rose but not the whole
rose I just see a corner of the rose or
something Then that's only like a split
second
I I look at his rose in his hair
I see a few pieces because I he told me
don't think about roast
then for
like three
seconds I I can see the pieces of the
rose but not the
roast
Uh and it's hard to explain but the what
I saw for a few seconds is
only shapes and colors no
rows So there's a red
color corner corner of the rose
There's a green green stick you know the
just green
line but no rose
Then suddenly my mind
uh make a perfect roast you
know but for just a
second uh I could see the
pieces without the roast
Okay Okay And he then he's like
okay Then he says let's do again
again Uh then he let me see the roast
Look at the
roast Uh and then he closed my eyes
again Then he said "Rose."
One word One word
Ros Then I start to get a picture of
Rose
Then he pushed my eyes open again
Look but don't look rose
[Music]
Just look at then I see just
pieces little red sharp you
know For just a
moment I can see
the pieces without the roast
Uh what's happening
[Music]
there
uh when a seed opens in your mind
uh there are some pieces in the
world red color
uh little corners angulos
then your eyes
uh they cannot see uh rose
they can see the
And they can see the
ship But the eye cannot decide what is
this
thing The eye and the brain is diff
separate The eye cannot see
rose I think the brain and the eye they
have telephone connection
And the eye says "Hey we got something
out here." Hello police
By the way the brain cannot see the
outside objects
directly The brain depends on the sense
organs What what we got what's out
there then the eye says "Oh we got red."
Red
What else you
got little triangles
You see the eye cannot decide what is
this
thing Uh scientist says the color and
the shade hit the cells at the back of
the eye
And then they take the shape and the
color but they they cannot decide what
is the
thing Then eyeball says to
bring we got
red We got
corners Then brain is like we're in the
garden
I think it's a rose you know And then
the brain sends a picture to the eyes
you
see And then the eyes put the picture on
the
pieces and that's a rose You see that
picture is coming out of your
seat And the only way to put the seeds
in your mind is to share a rose with
another
person Uh the good things in your
life you can only see the good things in
your life which you gave to other people
before
When when you share uh something
beautiful with
somebody you plant a seed for a
rose Then the the eye was coming Okay
All right
Uh then he touched his finger to the
ground We have two kinds of ants in
Arizona
One is a red ant They're pretty
big and they are very nasty
You know we dance around our my wife and
I when we they bite us and then we're
like then there's little black
ants me as much and they are very
peaceful They don't bite
When I took my cafe manager examination
and course from the government in my
state They
said you are required to kill the
roaches in your cafe
[Music]
Then but the
black they are super
clean It doesn't matter They can walk
everywhere
They actually clean up Olympian So
anyway Buddha touched the
ground Then he put the ant on the
rose Black ant
They are curious and
friendly Then he runs to the edge of the
roast you
know Then he's like "Ah he don't want to
fall
off." Then he runs to the other
side It's like a mountain for him you
know He's like "Then
uh then Gautama put the rose back on the
ground and the the ant went went home I
guess." Uh then he took the rose in his
hand
again and uh he put it to his own
face and he's looking at it like this
And I couldn't see the rose but I could
see his
eyes And he's like
super peaceful super
happy Then I'm thinking he must see
something different than what I did
Then he said "Uh listen When you first
open your
eyes you saw the pieces of the rose just
the colors and the
shapes And then your mind your seeds a
new picture came out and made a
rose But the ant
He look at the same
pieces and he sees ah
mountain for him it's very
frightening and uh then Buddha
said when I look at the same
colors and the same
shapes I see all of eternity
And I see the mind of every being in the
universe and I love
them at that
moment Then he like quiet and he closed
his
[Music]
eyes Then he reached out the rose again
to
E and he asked me a
question Who's
correct what is this
thing is it a
rose is it the Lord of
Death is it all the people in the
universe and perfect love
then because I'm sitting close to
Buddha I understood everything
quickly and I realized in his hand is
all three things
There's a
rose there's a
mountain and there's a universe of all
people
in his
hand And because I'm sitting close to
him I understand very
clearly there's nothing in his
head If if you have a
seed you will see a
rose If you have a black ant
seam you will see a mountain You know
if you have Buddha
uh you will see all the people in the
universe
By the way that's a cool
thing According to Buddhism there's no
end to the
universe If you get in a spaceship and
you fly fly you there you you will never
reach the end There is no
end But still if your mind is
clean you can meet everyone in the
universe in 20
minutes Everyone in this room can do it
You can meet everyone in the universe
All animals all
humans There's no number to
those But you can meet them all in 20
minutes
Okay if you see
emptiness Okay and that's what all these
classes are
for All right
He closed his hand
again Uh and he opened the the the hand
with the
flower He said "This time I want you to
see the whole
universe." And he goes
like and I'm
like and it's just all I see is a rose
And I'm like I'm sorry I I just see a
rose you know So
he says "I know." That's it
Because you can only see what your seeds
force you to
see You look at this and you see a
rose I see all the people in the
universe
And
then I closed my eyes and thought about
Rose I opened my eyes and see
Rose Then he just stopped
talking and he uh crossed his legs on
the
bench and he started to meditate
Uh and then I start to
meditate Uh so I will now I'll just read
Okay The silence
grew I lost the sounds of the
garden I lost the smell and the feel of
the
garden I lost the feeling of sitting in
the garden
Finally I lost the feeling of even
thinking And I lost the feeling of
myself and everything was perfectly
quiet I saw
emptiness and it was only then and I saw
it
There was nothing
else When it was over
things started to come
back I could feel myself coming
down and then I could feel myself
again Then
only only after I realized oh I saw
emptiness
on the in the hour that you see
emptiness you see many other
things So there's a list in the book
Yeah You don't believe So just enjoy
Okay I knew then that I had seen a
Buddha
Buddha Yeah
And I knew that Buddhas are
real I knew I will also become Buddha
uh within seven
lifetimes have to die six more times
something like this
Uh and and and then because of that I
knew really there is future
love because up till then you just heard
it from your teacher You don't you don't
know
really when you see emptiness you see
your future life
for the first time People ask me "Oh we
heard you have health problems."
I'm like "Yeah
and then they say "Aren't you worried?"
You
know and I said "Why?" He I know where
I'm
going I know who will take care of me
It's like it's like a really cool place
So I'm
like good
Okay So if you see
emptiness you don't ever have to worry
again even about death
Okay because you can see what's you it's
like you can see the restaurant You just
have to cross the street
Yeah Good Okay By the way I still take I
still eat medicine and things
Okay All right I'm try to stay for some
Uh then I knew the path is
correct When you see emptiness something
strange happens
Uh you understand that people will not
call you Michael in the
future i still didn't figure that out
Okay Notice
your name
change Maybe it's like when you get
married or something
uh then I knew uh the how those seven
lifetimes will
be and I know uh my parents and I know
who my teachers will
be and I know they will take care of me
from the first
day So I don't have anything to worry
about in the next seven
lives Now here's the interesting thing
that happens when you see
emptiness I knew that what I saw was
correct
True And I couldn't doubt it again
So you know thousand people can tell you
no you didn't see emptiness you
know you're
crazy you don't know anything
then you're like yeah okay I'm crazy
yeah because no one
can what you saw is true and you know
it's true and it's not just that you see
truth it's that you know you saw truth
and no
ever
can Doesn't matter what people say The
the biggest person in the world can say
you didn't do it You're like "Yeah
okay."
Nice Uh another thing happens on that
day You understand all the books are
correct
There's
300,000 books Buddhist books
Each one is as good as the
Bible And by the way the same
content but imagine you have 300,000
Bibles different
And they are all 100%
correct And you see
that and then you become like crazy
person We have to go to all the
libraries in the world
We got to find
them We got to take picture record them
Somebody say "I found the cure for
AIDS." You know I wrote it down
It works There's uh 40 million people
with AIDS in the world right
now Most of them will
die Then you have the
paper You have the what do you call it
the recipe
Then how will you feel about that paper
you're
like you know let's make copies
Let's make a AOL database
Let's make sure we translate
it Like how will you feel if you if
someone give you the only copy
40 million people will die if you lose
him
That's how Arya feels about the holy
books
Okay
Uh then uh I had an experience of loving
every living being
A light came out of my
chest A pillar of light Like it's not
uh It doesn't look like a Coca-Cola
straw
It looks like
a a rocket ship
And uh later I learned it's called prana
right and it came out no
color and it touched every living
[Music]
being And I spoke to each living being
in the
universe It's a very fun 20 minutes
You first you meet your
mom I don't care if she's alive or she's
not alive Doesn't
matter My mom was dead by that
time But uh she come to
me and she looks great
and uh but she looks a little bit
worried and I understand why why she's
worried
She has to die The people around her
have to
die Then I'm like "Don't worry Mom
Seven more lifetimes you know
then I'm going to be there you know and
you just hang hang on you know and I'm
coming as fast as I
can And you don't you don't have to
worry
just relax
Then she's like
then my father come
like that one by one My brothers
same uh mini
conversation You look a little bit
worried Yeah If you have to die you look
worried
also Then don't worry I'm going to take
care of everything You
know I know what to do You don't have to
die then Okay Oh wow Thank you
Okay Then uh one by one my aunts who I
met like two
times Then all my school
teachers sixth
grade fifth grade Yeah
The worst the worst one also came
worst school teacher
her name okay honestly it's Mrs But
the worst the
[Laughter]
worst deal then I'm like don't worry
I'll take care of
you then people I don't
know in my
city then people in all the
cities then people in other
countries one by one don't worry I'll
take care of you
Okay Thank you
Gracias Then start animals
Okay So I had a dog when I was a
kid His name is George Okay
And George come you know I'm
like I'm
like he's
[Music]
like then
cats
fish
birds all of them one by
one Not one chicken representative Each
chicken
[Music]
one by one I'm like I'll take care of
you
Then uh did something unbelievable Okay
Start the humans on the next
planet So I don't know where's that
planet I don't know I cannot point to
that place
Then the whole thing start over again
You cover all the humans animals
insects personal interview each one
Then after 20 minutes you
[Music]
finished every living being in the
universe
And I don't know either I'm a big liar
or it's something amazing
Either I'm a big liar or this is
something unbelievable
But it's true Really it's true As I sit
here it's true
And then
finishes And that's a bodhis sabra
That's a real
bodhis that it it's not just that you're
nice to people or something like that
and that's real
bodh
[Music]
okay you see your
death every human being uh secretly they
think all those stupid guys who are
dying I'm not like themos
Deep inside every human being thinks
"God those old people so stupid to get
old so stupid to die you know I'm not
going to do that
But Arya sees their
death and they believe
it
The earth's gravity is stronger than
you It's a
battle When you were two years old Kiri
you learn to fight gravity You learn to
walk
But in the end gravity wins
for everybody
And you lay down on the earth and you
die
[Music]
Interesting thing Okay I'm almost
finished Don't worry
[Music]
When the Arya comes down out of seeing
emptiness
directly they cannot see it
again in that you know they can't just
say "Oh I I want to see it again for 10
more minutes." You
know the karma is so
expensive You burn your karma credit
card for your whole life in 20 minutes
[Music]
Uh then you start to see things
uh like you see the pen the old
way You don't see it the new
way You cannot see that it's coming from
you You cannot
see some part of you still make
mistake Even the
aya what's the
difference the ara is wrong but he knows
he's wrong
But cannot stop it
You Latin America tour
teachers when you as you teach the
pen you are always seeing the pen wrong
I'm sorry but even in
Arya when they teach the pen at that
moment they cannot see the emptiness of
the pen
[Music]
Okay that's
all Okay All right
[Applause]
Uh so on this special day
uh let's do one minute meditation
that
um that we talked about these things
uh make a
prayer that someday they will happen to
you
If they didn't happen to you already I
don't
[Music]
know
Okay just one minute make a prayer
Then we can do uh sign books and photos
is okay
All right here we go
Okay good Thank you
Yes Yes